地          球          脉          动
我们星球上1/3的陆地是沙漠
A third of the land on our planet is desert.
这些地球脸上的大伤疤看似毫无生机
These great scars on the face of the Earth appear to be lifeless,
然而令人吃惊的是并非如此
but surprisingly none are.
在所有沙漠中 生命总能以某些方式闪现
In all of them life manages somehow to keep a precarious hold.
奇    幻    沙    漠
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
沙漠并非都是炎热的
Not all deserts are hot.
西伯利亚的寒风以50英里的时速
Fifty-mile-an-hour winds blowing in from Siberia
夹杂着风雪横扫蒙古戈壁沙漠
bring snow to the Gobi Desert in Mongolia.
虽然夏季气温高达50℃
From a summer high of 50 degrees centigrade
但是到了冬至却能降至零下40℃
the temperature in midwinter can drop to minus 40,
使得这里成为一片最荒凉的沙漠
making this one of the harshest deserts of all.
只有少许动物能适应 这种极端的气候变化
Few animals can survive these extreme changes.
野双峰驼
Wild Bactrian camels,
一种地球上最稀有的哺乳动物
one of the rarest mammals on the planet.
可能也是最坚韧的动物
And perhaps the hardiest.
它们最大的困难莫过于缺水
Their biggest problem is the lack of water,
尤其是现在——冬天
particularly now, in winter,
那里仅有的一点水也结成了冰
when the little there is is locked up as ice.
奇怪的是 这里的雪永远都不会融化
Surprisingly, snow here never melts.
又冷又干的空气使它们无法解冻
The air is just too cold and too dry for it to do so.
阳光把它们直接变成了水蒸气
The sun's rays turn it straight into vapour.
它们升华了
It evaporates.
可是这是唯一的水源
But it is the only source of water,
所以双峰驼只能吃雪
so Bactrian camels eat it.
在世界上其它地方
Elsewhere in the world
一只骆驼找到水坑后  能一次喝下200升水
a camel at a waterhole can drink as much as 200 litres during a single visit.
但在这里的饮水策略却是少而频繁
Here the strategy is to take little and often.
这当然有充分的理由
And with good reason,
因为肚子里装满雪将是致命的
for filling the stomach with snow could be fatal.
骆驼必须限定自己 每天只能吃10升左右的雪
The camels must limit themselves to the equivalent of just 10 litres a day.
冬季是交配时节
Winter is the time for breeding.
这种奇怪的表演是公双峰驼 吸引路过的母骆驼的一种方式
This extraordinary performance is a male Bactrian camel's way of attracting the attention of a passing female.
在夏天 骆驼不能远离水坑
In summer the camels can't stray far from waterholes.
可是现在 遍地都是唾手可得的雪
But now, with mouthfuls of snow lying everywhere
它们便能长途跋涉寻找配偶
they can travel widely in search of mates.
今天 这些沙漠专家的 野生数量已不足1000只
Today less than a thousand of these desert specialists remain in the wild.
戈壁尽管环境险恶 却是它们最后的据点
The Gobi, hostile though it is, is their last stronghold.
别的沙漠都和戈壁不太一样
There's no other desert quite like the Gobi,
为什么这里会成为沙漠呢
but why is this place a desert?
这里有一个简单而又重要的原因
There is one simple and massive cause -
喜马拉雅山脉
the Himalayas.
从南方过来的暖湿气流 撞上了这面巨大的屏障
Clouds blowing from the south hit this gigantic barrier.
在被迫抬升的过程中
As they're forced upwards
水汽在山坡上逐渐凝结
so they empty their moisture on the mountain slopes,
只有一小部分到达另一边的土地
leaving little for the land on the other side.
从太空中看 沙漠非常显眼
From the space deserts are very conspicuous.
绵延数百英里的沙丘像是一条条皱边花纹
Dunes of sand hundreds of miles long streak their surface.
由于没有植被覆盖
With no cloak of vegetation to conceal them
赤裸的岩石显露出奇特的造型
strange formations are exposed in the naked rock.
非洲的撒哈拉沙漠是世界上最大的沙漠
Africa's Sahara is the largest desert of all.
它的面积相当于美国
It's the size of the United States
也是全世界最大的沙尘源
and the biggest source of sand and dust in the entire world.
如此巨大的沙暴出现时毫无征兆
Sandstorms like these appear without warning
所到之处能见度骤降为零  几天内横扫的地区比英国还大
and reduce visibility for days over areas the size of Britain.
单峰驼——只有一个肉峰的骆驼  顶着沙暴大步行走
Dromedaries, single-humped camels, take these storms in their stride.
最重的沙子只能离开地面几米
The heaviest sand rises only a few metres above the ground,
但是尘埃却能被吹上5000多米高的天空
but the dust can be blown 5,000 metres up into the sky.
夹杂着沙粒的强风
The ferocious wind, armed with grains of sand,
塑造了各种沙漠地形
is the agent that shapes all deserts.
爬行动物的皮肤覆盖着鳞甲  能抵御刺痛的沙粒
Reptiles have armoured scaly skins that protect them from the stinging grains.
而昆虫则得遭受猛烈“炮火”的轰击
For insects the bombardment can be very severe indeed.
唯一的藏身之处当然是在沙子下面
The only escape is below the surface.
随着风的起落、侵蚀和旋绕
As the winds rise and fall, swallow and eddy
沙子被堆成了一座座沙丘
so they pile the sand into dunes.
这些沙漠布景可宽达数百英里
These sand scenes can be hundreds of miles across.
在纳米比亚 风塑造了 一些世界上最大的沙丘
In Namibia the winds have built some of the biggest dunes in the world.
这些巨型沙丘高达300多米
Star dunes like these can be 300 metres high.
斜坡上吹起的沙粒 在沙丘顶部的边棱处飞扬
Grains, swept up the flanks, are blown off the crests of the ridges
所以沙丘移动的部分只是顶部
so it's only the tops that are moving.
这些沙丘的主体 可能已有5000多年未曾移动
The main body of these dunes may not have shifted for 5,000 years.
岩石很难抵挡风沙持续不断的摧残
Few rocks can resist the continuous blast of the sand carrying wind.
这些石头如今矗立在埃及的白色沙漠中
These outcrops are standing in Egypt's White Desert.
但它们也坚持不了多久
But they will not do so for much longer.
它们正被无情地凿碎 变成更多的沙粒
They're being inexorably chiseled away and turned into more sand.
现在 这些严重侵蚀的石块 已被放逐在沙海之中
Now lumps of heavily eroded rocks have been marooned in a sea of sand.
这些高达100多米的锯齿般的石锥
These jagged pyramids a hundred metres tall
曾经是一整块岩石高地的一部分
were once part of a continuous rocky plateau.
强悍的风沙最终将使它们完全消失
The blasting sand will eventually eliminate them altogether.
风的无情力量总是使沙漠的面貌不断改变
The relentless power of the wind ensures that the face of a desert is continually changing.
但是有一样东西永远都会存在
But there is one constant presence -
沙漠的太阳
the desert sun.
太阳的热力使水蒸发
The sun's heat and power to evaporate water
这对所有生活在这里的动物的 身体和习性都有极其深远的影响
has had a profound effect on the bodies and habits of everything that lives here.
在这里 太阳将会成为杀手
This sun potentially is a killer.
红大袋鼠必须意识到这一点
And the red kangaroos must acknowledge that.
此时 太阳还未升起
Right now, while the sun is low,
并没有直接危及到生命
there's no immediate cause for concern.
但是这种情况不会持续多久
But this situation won't last long.
澳大利亚是世界上最干旱的大陆  整个白天酷热难当
Australia is the world's most arid continent with blistering daytime temperatures.
每过一小时 气温就将升高5℃
Every hour the temperature rises by five degrees centigrade.
热度很快就会达到临界点
Soon the heat will reach a critical point.
任何一只呆在外面的袋鼠 都将面临中暑的威胁
Any kangaroo out in the open is in serious danger of overheating.
待到阳光最毒辣之时  地面温度已升高至70℃
In the full sun the temperature on the ground soars to 70 degrees.
到了正午 太阳的炙焰 迫使它们不得不寻找庇荫处
By midday the radiation is so intense they must take shelter.
在树荫下 它们虽然避开了太阳的能量
In the shade they're shielded from much of the sun's energy
但它们的体温仍在升高
but their body temperature can still rise.
所以它们将唾液抹在前臂上
So they lick saliva on to their forearms
那里的血管网比较贴近皮肤表层
where there is a network of blood vessels close to the surface of the skin
因此 当唾液蒸发时 血液也能得到冷却
and, as the saliva evaporates, their blood is cooled.
这幅热影像能证明这种方法非常有效
This thermal image shows just how effective the process is.
身上蓝色的部分是较冷的部位
The blue areas on the body are the cooler parts.
唾液干了之后还得重新抹上
As the saliva dries it has to be replaced
袋鼠真正排放出去的体液也就是这些
and this is a real drain on the kangaroo's body fluids.
即使是在树荫下 土地照样被烤得火热
Even in the shade the earth is baking hot
于是袋鼠刨去灼烫的表层沙土
so the kangaroos dig away the warmed topsoil
贴近下面较冷的地面
to get at the cooler ground beneath.
通过呆在树荫下  并利用舔唾液的方法控制体温
By staying in the shade and licking to control their body temperature
袋鼠便能熬过一天中最热的时段
kangaroos manage to get through the hottest part of the day
而不至于中暑
without heat stroke.
但是对于大多数沙漠动物来说
But for the majority of desert animals
光凭这些手段还不足以在此生存
this strategy would not be enough for survival.
非洲的耳廓狐长有奇特的大耳  它们能散发热量
The extraordinary ears of the fennec foxes of Africa radiate heat
不过动物也有其它保持凉爽的方法
but the animals have another way of keeping cool.
它们白天呆在地下
They spend their days underground
直到日落之后才会出现
and only emerge at sunset.
夜晚的情况变得很不一样
Darkness brings huge changes.
在撒哈拉沙漠中  晚上的气温会下降整整30℃
In the Sahara the temperature can drop as much as 30 degrees during the night,
在如此凉爽的时候  小耳廓狐也能尽情玩耍
so it's cool enough to allow these desert fox cubs to play.
此时各种各样的动物都开始现身
All sorts of creatures now appear
包括一些意想不到的动物
including some really unexpected ones.
蟾蜍长着透水的皮肤
Toads have permeable skins
若是在白天的高温下  它们很快就会因为脱水而死
and would quickly die from desiccation out in the daytime heat.
所以只有到了晚上它们才能离开庇护所
It's only now that they can leave shelter.
蝎子也是同样的情况
The same is true for scorpions,
尽管它们的外壳其实并不透水
even though their shells are actually watertight.
事实上 大多数小型沙漠动物 都是夜行动物
In fact, most small desert creatures are nocturnal.
所以只有此时你才能判断 沙漠中究竟有多少生物
so it's only now that you can judge just how much life there can be in the desert.
可是水分在晚上也会损耗  必须在什么时候想办法补充
But moisture, lost even at night, has to be replaced sometime somehow
这一问题支配着所有沙漠动物的生活
and that problem dominates the lives of all desert dwellers.
智利的阿塔卡马沙漠
The Atacama in Chile.
这里是世界上最干旱的沙漠
This is the driest desert in the world.
有的地方可能连续5年不会下一滴雨
Some parts may not see rain for fifty years
既然有了这一纪录
and with such a record
不难想象这个地方定是彻底的荒芜
you'd expect the place to be completely barren.
这些是南美洲的骆驼——原驼
These are South America's camels, guanacos.
它们非常善于保存水分
They're very good at conserving moisture
但它们仍须定期补充水
but they nonetheless need a regular supply of water.
其中一部分水取自仙人掌花
They get it partly from cactus flowers
但这里又牵扯出另一个问题
but that explanation raises another question.
仙人掌为何能在这个无雨地带生存
How do the cacti survive without rain?
热浪抽干了地面上所有的水分
Hot winds suck all the moisture from the surface of the land.
显然 这里必须有其它东西 能代替雨水的作用
Clearly there must be something else that takes the place of rain.
答案就是一股与陆地平行的寒冷洋流
The secret is a cold sea current that runs parallel to the land.
冷水使得上方的暖湿气流冷却
The cold water cools the moist warm air above it
形成一团团的雾霾
and that produces banks of fog.
与此同时 吹向海岸的风将雾气带上陆地
At the same time wind blowing on to the shore sweeps the fog inland.
不久之后 雾凝结成了露水
Before long the cacti are dripping with dew.
雾经常会出现
The fog is so regular
就连喜湿的地衣也能在仙人掌上生长
that moisture loving lichens are able to grow on the cacti
它们像海绵一样吸收着水汽
and they absorb liquid like a sponge.
在一个几乎没有雨的地方
In the land of almost no rain
这些宝贵的水滴是许多动物的救命物资
these precious drops are life-savers for many different creatures.
在更远的内陆地区  空气一直十分灼热 水汽无法凝结
Further inland the air remains so warm that its moisture does not condense
因此这个狭长地带实际上是 阿塔卡马沙漠中唯一的生命绿洲
so this slender strip of desert is virtually the only part of the Atacama where life can exist.
如果没有雾
Without the fog,
这片土地也将成为不毛之地
this land, too, would be empty.
原驼尽量舔吮露水
The guanacos make the most of the dew
因为它们不会保留多久
but it will not remain for long.
1～2小时后 太阳将使它们蒸发
In an hour or two the sun will have burnt it off
仙人掌表面将回复干燥
and dry the surface of the cacti.
亚利桑那州的索诺兰沙漠 并不像阿塔卡马沙漠那样干旱
The Sonoran desert in Arizona is not quite so dry as the Atacama -
这里有时会下一些雨
some rain does fall.
可是降雨次数很少
But it is infrequent
一旦雨水到来
and when it does arrive
所有动植物都必须 做好准备尽量地利用它们
animals and plants have to be ready to make the most of it.
要下雨了
And it's coming.
当夏季季风吹来时
When the summer monsoon blows in
巨大的弁庆柱 ——一种世界上最大的仙人掌
the giant saguaros, one of the biggest of all cacti,
准备充分利用雨水
are ready to take full advantage of it.
暴风雨过后 弁庆柱 用又长又浅的根系吸收水分
After a rainstorm the saguaro's long shallow root system sucks up the water
茎上的皱褶使之能迅速膨胀
and the pleats on its trunk enable it to expand rapidly.
吸饱水后 弁庆柱的茎干中 已储存了5吨左右的水
When full, a saguaro stem can store up to five tonnes of water
这足以帮助它们度过几个月的旱季
and that's enough to see it through many months of drought.
这些立柱般的巨型植物 为橙腰啄木鸟提供了住所
The trunks of these huge plants provide homes for the gila woodpecker.
不过鸟并非唯一从仙人掌那里 获得好处的动物
But birds are not the only animals to benefit from the presence of the cacti.
在夏季的4个星期里
During four weeks of the summer
弁庆柱在晚上开花 吸引了不少拜访者
the saguaros bloom at night to attract visitors.
这些花中装满了花粉和花蜜
The pollen and nectar with which these flowers are loaded
吸引了长鼻蝠和长舌蝠
attract long-nosed and long-tongued bats.
蝙蝠数日前离开墨西哥以躲避酷暑
The bats left Mexico a few days earlier to escape the heat of summer
正向北飞往美国南部
and are on their way north to the southern United States.
要想到达那里  它们必须穿越索诺兰沙漠
To get there, they have to cross the Sonoran desert.
不过这片沙漠很大
But the desert is so big
它们一年中大部分时间都无法穿越这里
that for most of the year they would be unable to cross it.
现在 有了正在开花的弁庆柱
Now, with the saguaro in bloom,
它们便能在旅途中得到休整
they can refuel on the way.
看来弁庆柱进化出的 这种成功的储水方式
So the saguaro's success in developing a way to store water
如今已关系到大部分 在此生活和旅行的动物
is now crucial to most of the animals that live or even travel through this land.
缺少雨水的环境塑造了这些沙漠中的图标
The scarcity of rain determined the shape of this icon of the desert
尽管水很少 但它也和风一样  造就了各种地形
but water, scarce thought it is, has also, like the wind, shaped the land itself.
在犹他州的沙漠中
In the deserts of Utah
古老的河流冲开岩壁 不断拓宽这些峡谷
ancient rivers flowing across sandstone country steadily widen their canyons
直到把其间的土地削凿成 今天这样的尖峰和石塔
until now the land between them has been reduced to spires and pinnacles.
由于几乎没有土壤保留地表水分
With little or no soil to retain the water on the surface of the land
这里的生物极其稀少
life here is scarce indeed.
当资源有限的时候
And when resources are limited,
冲突自然不可避免
conflict is never far away.
这些是努比亚羱羊
These are Nubian ibex
它们正摆好架势准备激战
and they are squaring up for a duel.
冲突一旦爆发
And when trouble starts,
聪明的羱羊很清楚 最好的战术就是占领制高点
a smart ibex knows that the best thing to do is to gain higher ground.
这些其实是次级别的公羱羊
These are actually subordinate male ibex,
但它们的战斗依然十分激烈
but their fights are nonetheless serious.
失败一次或许意味着将永远失去生育权
Losing one might mean never getting the chance to breed ever.
同级别的参赛者在此公平竞争
When competitors are evenly matched as they are here,
决斗会持续一小时左右
duels can last for an hour.
高温下的战斗确实很耗费体力
In this heat the effort is trully exhausting.
但是这里的获胜者会获得重要的排名  一步步到达公羊排行榜的第一位
But victory here will gain important ranking points on a male's way to the top.
这类决斗非常危险
There's so much at stake
而且并不总是公平的
that not all play fair.
这场战斗已经分出了胜负
The battle has produced the winner,
但是最后的奖品仍然不属于它
but the ultimate prize is not his yet.
它通常属于拥有统治权的公羊
That currently belongs to the dominant male ibex.
它的地位为它赢得了一群忠诚的母羊
His rank earns him the loyalty of a harem of females
它们一起紧跟着它穿越沙漠
and they follow him closely as he travels across this desert
寻找水和食物
searching for foof and water.
它不必浪费时间寻找配偶
He doesn't have to waste time looking for mates -
它们都是它的妻子
they're his for the taking,
所以它要做的只是保证它们健康精壮
so he can concentrate with them on keeping fit and healthy.
蜥蜴是沙漠专家
Lizards are desert specialists.
在这里 它们的数量多得惊人
But here, their numbers are extraordinary.
非洲南部的这些岩缝中 容纳着世界上最大的蜥蜴群
These crevices in South Africa contain the highest density of lizards in the world.
它们叫做扁石蜥——因为显而易见的原因
They're called flat lizards for obvious reasons,
它们炫耀自己五颜六色的腹部 是为了争夺领地
and they flaunt their multi-coloured bellies in territorial disputes.
它赢了
He's made his point,
现在该是寻找食物的时候了
and now it's time to find some food.
随着白天气温的升高
As the day warms up,
蜥蜴离开它们藏身的岩缝
the lizards move away from their cracks
奔向峡谷底部
and head down to the bottom of the gorge.
它们的目标是这条小河
Their goal is the river.
河边没有一点食物
There is no food at the edge,
但是这条沙漠河流却藏着一个秘密
but this desert river holds a secret.
每天 成千上万的蚋从奔腾的河水中羽化
Each day blackfly rise from turbulent stretches of the river.
这就是蜥蜴到此的目的
This is what the lizards have come for.
蚋不会降落
The black fly never land,
所以蜥蜴必须跳起来捕食
so the lizards have to leap for their food.
每只身怀绝技的小蜥蜴 一天能吃掉50多只小虫
In one day each of these acrobatic little lizards may catch 50 flies.
尽管已有几百只蜥蜴在此捕猎  这里仍聚集着无数飞虫
There are plenty of flies to go round, even with hundreds of lizards competing for them.
在远离这些急流的地方  扁石蜥的数量则要少得多
Away from these rapids flat lizard populations are found much smaller numbers.
但在这里 一种特别的资源 带动了另一物种的兴起
But here one unusual abundance has produced another.
沙漠的形成是因为缺少水
Deserts are created by the lack of water,
可是这里杀死动物的 真正原因并非炎热和缺水
but what actually kills animals here is not heat or thirst,
而是缺少食物
but lack of food.
那么在地球上 如此巨大的植食动物是如何 在这个寸草不生的地方生存的呢
So how on earth does a plant-eater this size survive in a place apparently totally devoid of vegetation?
纳米比亚的大象是非洲最能吃苦的动物
Elephants in Namibia are the toughest in Africa.
它们必须如此
And they need to be.
仅有的少量食物也非常分散
What little food exists is so dispersed
所以这些大象每天得走上50英里
that these elephants walk up to 50 miles a day
沿着干涸的河床搜寻一些可以吃的东西
as they travel up the dry river channels searching for something to eat.
有时这个愿望看起来根本不可能实现
At times the task looks truly helpless.
大象似乎不属于有这种地形的地方
Elephants may seem out of place in this landscape,
但它们并非唯一意外的物种
but they're not the only ones.
奇怪的是 狮子也生活在这里
Amazingly, lions live here, too.
热带大草原的竞争促使鼎盛的 狮群数量达到20只 甚至更多
In savanah country huge herds of games support prides containing 20 lions or more.
而若想在此生存  狮子必须改变它们的习性
But to live here lions have had to change their habits -
狮群规模小了很多
prides are much smaller
但家族的疆土面积却大大增加
and their home ranges are very much bigger.
这里还有另一个问题
And there's an added problem -
它们的食物总是在移动
their food is always on the move.
和大象一样
Like the elephants,
狮子也必须长途跋涉 寻找生存所需的食物
the lions must travel great distances to find enough to live on.
可是狮子并不是什么地方都能去的
But lions can't go everywhere -
它们不会试着爬过一座沙丘
they won't attempt to cross this field of sand dunes
长角羚很清楚这一点
and the oryx know it.
狮子必须耐心等待 长角羚离开安全的沙丘
The lions must wait for the oryx to leave the safety of the dunes,
因为它们最后总得寻找食物和水
which eventually they must to find food and water.
介时狮子就能伏击它们
And then the lions will ambush them.
大象找到了一些它们最喜欢吃的食物
The elephants have found some of their favourite food.
草是所有大象的主食
Grasses are the staple diet of all elephants,
但这群象却忙着挖掘草根
but this herd concentrates on digging up the roots,
因为草根中的营养和水分比茎干多得多
which have more nutrition and moisture than the stems.
这一举措在这个资源 严重匮乏的地方显得极为重要
It's the sort of behaviour that can make all the difference in a place of serious shortages.
然而所有这一切即刻就将发生改变
Yet all this can change in an instant.
许多沙漠的命运都由远方的雨水决定
The fortunes of many deserts are ruled by distant rains.
这些水来自100英里之外的山地降雨
This water fell as rain in mountains more than a hundred miles away.
它叫做“瞬时洪水”
It's known as a flash flood
之所以这么叫是因为 这些水可能仅仅流淌一天左右
and called that because the water may run for just a single day.
而且一年最多也只发生1～2次
It's an event that only happens once or twice a year at the most.
布满沙子的河床像是一张巨大的吸水纸
The sandy riverbed acts like a giant strip of blotting paper
水一边流淌一边被它吸去
sucking up the water as soon as it appears.
这里的每一寸土壤都已被河水润湿
But every square metre of soil moistened by this river
为生活在这里的动物们带来了生机
will increase the chances of survival for those that live here.
水坑里暂时填满了水
Waterholes are filled temprorarily.
非洲其它地方的大象每天都会喝水
Elsewhere in Africa elephants drink every day,
但这里缺水的现状
but the lack of water here
意味着沙漠里的大象 只能每隔四五天喝饱一回
means that desert elephants can only refill their tanks once every four or five days.
短短一周内 瞬时洪水浸润过的 土地上已长出了青草
Within a week the flash flood has produced a flush of green,
远远多于从沙丘返回的长角羚的需求
more than enough to draw the oryx out of the dunes.
这是它们仅有的积累食物储备的机会
It's a rare chance for them to build up their food reserves.
洪水也让狮子过上了好日子
The flood has made life easier for the lions, too.
这只长角羚的肉最多 能维持整个家族一星期左右
The flesh of this oryx will keep the family going for a week at the most.
此时 狩猎暂时变得容易许多  河道也穿上了一件绿装
But for a while the hunting will be easier, now that river channel has turned green.
狮子和长角羚的美好时光十分短暂
The good times for lions and oryx are brief,
但就是这些短暂的日子使它们 得以全年在沙漠中生活
but these are the short moments that make it possible to live in deserts the year round.
死亡谷是地球上最热的地方
Death Valley is the hottest place on Earth.
然而这个“火炉”也会因为水而发生改变
Yet even this furnace can be transformed by water.
一场大雨使得在地下沉睡了30多年的 种子迸发出生命的活力
A single shower can enable seeds that have lain dormant for 30 years or more to burst into life.
这里已有一个世纪 没有像现在这样开满鲜花
And there hasn't been a bloom like this one for a century.
死亡谷中的花期很短
The periods of boom in Death Valley are short.
但它们发生的次数 足以保证生命长盛不衰
but they're just frequent enough to keep life ticking over.
植物的突然兴盛是 所有沙漠动物都盼望的事
A sudden flush of vegetation is what every desert dweller waits for,
一旦发生 它们必须尽可能地利用它
and when it happens they must make the most of it.
好日子到来时 地球上没有其它物种
There is no other species on the planet that responds
能像沙漠蝗那样迅速而又戏剧性地作出反应
as quickly and as dramatically to the good times as the desert locust.
在地下埋藏了20年的虫卵开始孵化
Eggs that have remained in the ground for 20 years begin to hatch.
沙漠蝗的若虫是跳跃能手
The young locusts are known as hoppers,
在这一阶段 它们还不能飞
for at this stage they're flightless.
它们循着萌发的草香寻找新的用餐场所
They find new feeding grounds by following the smell of sprouting grass.
一般说来 若虫需要 经过4周才能变成成虫
Normally it takes four weeks for hoppers to become adults,
但如果条件允许 譬如现在
but when the conditions are right as now
它们的生长过程就会切换到快车道
their development switches to the fast track.
当一个地方的植物即将吃光时
As the vegetation in one place begins to run out
长着翅膀的成虫便释放出信息素  即一些气味信号
the winged adults release pheromones - scent messages,
提醒蝗群中的其它成员它们应该动身了
which tell others in the group that they must move on.
蝗群合并之后
And when groups merge,
形成了一团蝗虫云
they form a swarm.
成虫每天的进食量相当于自己的体重
An adult locust eats its entire body weight every day,
而整团蝗虫云能消耗掉数百吨植物
and a whole swarm can consume literally hundreds of tonnes of vegetation.
它们必须不停地迁徙
They have to keep on moving.
沙漠蝗御风而行
The swarm travels with the wind -
这是最省力的飞行方式
it's the most energy-saving way of flying.
随着风向迁徙意味着 它们总是飞向低压地区
Following the flow of wind means that they're always heading toward areas of low pressure,
那里正是风雨交加的地方 植物定能生长
places where wind meets rain and vegetation starts to grow.
在飞行过程中
As they fly,
一团蝗虫云也会和其它蝗虫云汇合
swarms join up with other swarms
从而形成巨大的灾害  无数“瘟神”组成的大军绵延长达40英里
to form gigantic plagues several billions strong and as much as 40 miles wide.
它们将把一路上能吃的东西 全部吃得精光
They will consume every edible thing that lies in their path.
这是地球上最壮观的景象之一
This is one of planet Earth's greatest spectacles.
很少能看见如此大的规模
It's rarely seen on this scale
而且也不会持续多久
and it won't last long.
待到食物耗尽之时
Once the food is gone,
无数蝗虫拍打翅膀时的喧哗将不复存在
the steady roar of a billion beating locust wings will once again
再次取代它的只是沙漠中呼啸的风声
be replaced by nothing more than the sound of the desert wind.